ILGWU. David Melman papers, 5780/152
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. David Melman papers, bulk
1974-1992.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Melman, David.
5780/152
71 cubic feet
71 linear feet
Records
Contains the files of Executive Assistant to the President David Melman from 1974 to 1992. Included are extensive company files which include correspondence and other materials relating to contract negotiations. Also included are records on General Executive Board meetings and ILGWU conventions, as well as general subject files.
5521558
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
June 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, June 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Scope and Contents
Contains the files of Executive Assistant to the President David Melman from 1974 to 1992. Included are extensive company files which include correspondence and other materials relating to contract negotiations. Also included are records on General Executive Board meetings and ILGWU conventions, as well as general subject files.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Melman, David.; Melman, David.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5521558
- Arbitrations: Jonathan Logan and Subsidiaries, 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Re Jonathan Logan and subsidiaries: Act III, Alice Stuart, Butte Knitting Mills, Mercer Dress, Modern Juniors, Misty Harbor, Oxford Fashions (Oxford, Alabama), R&K Originals, Spartan Undies, Tracey Fashions (Chambersburg, PA), Trebor Knitting Mills
- Arbitrations: Jonathan Logan and Subsidiaries, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Audit Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Audit statements, arbitration requests, letters of agreement (settlement of claims); lists of contractors (union and nonunion); re Modern Juniors, RoseMarie Reid, Calhoun Mfg, Belmont
- Audit Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Act III, 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Notification of plant closings (annotated), audit reports/financial statements, master agreement. Re: Jonathan Logan, Debra Fashions, Lynn Fashions, Act III, Butte Knitting, Misty Harbor, Plaza Mfg, Terence Fashions, Spartanburg Undies
- Belmont Manufacturing, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Arbitration requests re vacation pay, length-of-service pay at closed plant, also known as Burns Apparel Company
- Butte Knitting Mills, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Contract proposals for Act III, Andrea Knit, Debra Knit, Roanoke Fashions, Butte Kitting Mills, Calhoun Mfg. Kingston Dress, Mercer Dress, Modern Juniors, Kim Fashions, Act II, and Transportation Dept; master agreement with Jonathan Logan; audit report showing Butte/Jonathon piece rate schedule, 1979-82; correspondence re use and misuse of union labels; complaint filed with NLRB v. Oxford Fashions (Oxford, Alabama), 1980; notification of David Knit plant closing (Northumberland, PA); memo to president Sol Chaikin from exec VP Wilbur Daniels re meeting with Jonathan Logan president Richard Schwartz re outsourcing to nonunion shops; Department of Labor decisions granting (1970, 1979) and denying (1982) worker adjustment assistance for plant closings, comment by union legal dept.; lists of jobs lost at closed plants; analysis of salaries and pension benefits, Malden Mills, Lawrence plant, comparison with other union plants; correspondence re Kingston Dress internal union litigation, 1983-84
- Butte Knitting Mills, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Debra Knit, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Contract proposals, payroll records, production record; re work process procedures, wages
- Kingston Dress Company, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Internal union memos re Duty of Fair Representation (DFR) suit against the union by laid-off workers of the closed Kingston Dress Co; correspondence with Act III officials
- Modern Juniors, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Correspondence re arbitration decision over severance pay; arbitration awards and requests re shutdown of division and associated plants; union demands re Butte Knitting, Act III, Modern Juniors, 1979; audit of pay data at Clinton, NC, plant showing extremely low piece-work wages, 1979; Department of Labor decision granting trade adjustment assistance for laid- off workers at closed Calhoun Mfg plant, 1984: Memos re benefits at Clinton (NC), Calhoun (St. Matthews, SC), & Belmont (Barnesville, OH) plants; letter from Jonathan Logan attorney S.Z. Cohen informing exec. VP Wilbur Daniels of closing of several Butte Kitting and Act III plants, 1982; memo to VP Nick Bonanno from exec. VP Daniels re arbitration over shutdown of cutting facility in Baltimore & consolidation at Spartanburg, 1984; survey report of nonunion plants Three G's Mfg and Ralph A. Bryant Co., in Tennessee; audit reports of funds owed by several plants to union for use of nonunion contractor; proceedings of arbitration hearing for funds owed to union for use of nonunion contractors, 1982; meeting minutes & correspondence re settlement agreement on use of nonunion contractors & nonunion cutting contractors by Modern Juniors & Rose Marie Reid, 1983; memo to president Sol Chaikin from exec. VP Daniels re licensing agreement of Jonathan Logan name to Kayser-Roth, payment of damages for use of nonunion contractors, 1983
- Spartanburg Transportation, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  1984: Memo to VP Nick Bonanno from exec. VP Wilbur Daniels re arbitration over shutdown of cutting facility in Baltimore & consolidation at Spartanburg; legal brief in arbitration grievance over Jonathan Logan Belmont Mfg./Modern Juniors truck driver; 1980: letter from exec. VP Daniels to Jonathan Logan president Richard Schwartz notifying him of submission of arbitration over truck driver wage grievance, comments on company's ongoing lack of cooperation with union VP Nick Bonanno; grievance reports re truck driver wage, impassable highways
- Thomson Manufacturing Company, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Correspondence re arbitration hearing on plant closing; master agreement, 1984
- Trebor Knitting Mills, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Contract proposals, Westminster Knit, 1985; severance pay schedules, 1983; list of employee earnings and hours for five different weeks between Aug. 19–December 19, 1982; pay records for cutters; arbitration adjournment notice with Ryerson Undergarment, 1989
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: General, 1989-1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Letter from Leslie Fay senior VP/CFO Polishan re disputed contributions to benefit funds for North American Knitting, copy of check, 1989; lists of monthly incentive averages for craft categories and union label counts, 1990; letter from Alabama commissioner of labor offering assistance in resolving contract negotiations, 1991; memos from ILG director of Northeast, Western Pennsylvania, and Ohio Department re increasing work going to Chinatown and overseas, 1990-91; letter to ILG president Mazur from locked-out workers in Wilkes-Barre, PA, 1991; letters from director of ILG Health & Safety Department re ergonomics intervention study with Mt. Sinai Hospital and Univ. of Lowell, re OSHA citations and abatement plans, re conference on repetitive motion injury, 1990; master agreement, June 1, 1988 – May 31, 1991; letter of agreement extending master agreement to July 31, 1991; agreement with Julie Fashions I and II, 1990; original signed agreement re Westminster Knit Unit of Jonathan Logan Division of United Merchants and Manufacturers (UMM), 1990; union proposals re wages, health benefits, etc., 1991; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: General, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Memos re non-union provisions of master agreement and concerns about non-union Head Sportswear, Leslie Fay's rights to acquire non-union plants, non-union work by Jorca (Hialeah, FL) for Personal Sportswear division, 1987; letters of agreement on imports, /1/88, 12/11/87 and 6/1/85; import analysis, 1984-87 for various subsidiaries; meeting minutes re Leslie Fay Dresses' desire to use "Made in U.S.A" hangtags; memo re results of efforts to organize non-union shops: Julie I & II, Joy, Solomon (Tallahassee, FL), Stephanie (Roanoke, Alabama), Advancetex, & Jorca; meeting minutes re negotiations for damages settlement for use of non-union shops, esp. Paulette Fashions; letter of agreement re volume differentials; master agreement items needing resolution, 1984; arbitration request re vacation benefits; memos between Sol Chaikin, pres. ILGWU, and John Pomerantz, pres. Leslie Fay, re points of agreement on non-union subcontractors; letter of agreement re acquisition of union shop Summit Sportswear; memo re agreement with Personal Sportswear (Morrow, GA) re holidays, health plan contributions; summary of contract labor at Rhonda Fashions, Patti Fashions, Overton Mfc; union handbill distributed at Head Sportswear (Baltimore & Columbia, MD) re organizing campaign; handwritten meeting minutes; report on Head Ski Company; letter from Leslie Fay pres. re unresolved issues for master agreement and supplement agreements
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: General, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Summary of unresolved issues re master agreement, including import clause, and re supplemental agreements at Personal Sportswear (Morrow, GA), Stephanie Fashions (Roanoke, Alabama) Castleberry Knits (NY), Kathryn Conover (Minneapolis, MN), New York sample rooms, termination of Fay's Closet division (Boston, MA), 1983; report on non-union North American Knitting, producing for Castleberry, 1983; master agreement changes re plant closing, relocations, layoffs, 1983; correspondence & agreement re Kathryn Conover (Minneapolis, MN) union status (Oct-Nov 1982, Dec 1983); signed agreement re imports, 1982; export license for Outlander (NY) for shipment from Hong Kong, 1981; draft of agreement re National Retirement Fund; correspondence w/ Leslie Fay controller Polishan re disputed contributions to retirement and health funds, 1979
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Audits, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Personal Sportswear (Morrow, GA) audit of non-union contractors, 10/83-12/84; imports analysis for subsidiaries, with addresses of suppliers, 1985-86; Personal Sportswear and Breckenridge, percentages of union vs non-union contracting, 11/1/83-12/31/84; monthly reports on non-union contracting, various companies, 1982-86; Misty Harbor summary of imports (suppliers), 1983 and 1985
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Audit Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Correspondence w/ Leslie Fay pres. Terwilliger re imports and use of non-union contractors, 1988; correspondence w/ Leslie Fay controller Polishan re disputed contributions to retirement and health funds, 1979-84
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Clippings, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Women's Wear Daily, Crain's New York Business, NY Post, Citizen's Voice (Wilkes- Barre, PA), Overton County News (Livingston, TN), WNEP-TV (ABC, Wilkes-Barre, PA) re profits and losses, bankruptcies, brand consolidation, brand repositioning, new mass market ventures, licensing agreements, acquisitions, market expansion to United Kingdom, executive compensation, executive management changes, market trends, automation, merchandising strategies, litigation, NAFTA, health investigation by OSHA
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Clippings, Accounting Scandal, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Women's Wear Daily, New York Times, Wall Street Journal, Times Leader (Wilkes-Barre, PA), Citizen's Voice (Wilkes-Barre, PA)
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Corporate Report, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  SEC filing, annual report
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Corporate Reports, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  SEC filings, FY 1988 & 89; lists of subsidiaries, company newsletter
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Negotiations, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Master agreement, 6/1/91; memo re company plans to reposition brand, 1993; memorandum of agreement re plant consolidations, 1993; letter re cost-of-living increases; letters of agreement re imports, no strike, no lockout, shift differential, transportation to medical treatment for injuries on the job, union orientation meetings for new employees; drafts of master agreement ("company's version," "sent to company") 6/1/88-5/31/91; Stephanie agreement, June 1, 1989, with correspondence re progress on Breckenridge and other supplemental agreements; handwritten notes from negotiation meetings, correspondence re points of negotiation re Stephanie supplement, Sportswear supplement, New York sample rooms agreement
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Negotiations [folder 1 of 4], 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Drafts of master agreement, 6/1/88-5/31/91; letter on imports
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Negotiations [folder 2 of 4], 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Drafts of master agreement, 6/1/88-5/31/91; letters of agreement re no strike, no lockout; imports; list of Leslie Fay divisions and plants; handwritten agenda
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Negotiations [folder 3 of 4], 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Drafts of master agreement, 6/1/88-5/31/91; correspondence
- Leslie Fay Companies, Incorporated: Negotiations [folder 4 of 4], 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Handwritten meeting minutes
- Breckenridge of Boston, 1988-1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Drafts of supplemental agreement (some heavily hand annotated), 6/1/88; correspondence re points of negotiation: cost of living adjustments, prescription drug coverage, sick & vacation pay, pension fund, severance pay; 1982 signed agreement (Breckenridge, Victoire, Fay's Closet, all in Boston); 1991draft agreement; audit correspondence
- Breckenridge of Boston, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Castleberry Knits, Knitgood Workers, UKMI (NY), 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Inter-company memo discussing unique qualities of yarn manufactured by North American Knitting Mills (Mansfield, OH), 1985; arbitration correspondence re use of non-union North American Knitting; supplemental agreements, 6/1/88 and 6/1/82; agreement between United Knitwear Manufacturers League and the Knitgood Workers' Union (ILG), 6/1/88; lists of minimum rates for specific crafts, 6/1/85, 86, 87, 89, 90; excerpts of terms from current and prior contracts, 1988
- Julie I and II Agreements: Tuscarora and Minorsville, PA, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Edited drafts of supplemental agreements, 1991, 92; memorandum of agreement re volume differential, 1994; audit report re layoffs, 1993
- Pennsylvania Plants: General Agreements, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Supplemental agreement, 6/1/85; correspondence re incorporation of consent award amending agreement re determination and pay for substandard workers, 1988; drafts of and final signed agreement, 5/26/88; drafts of supplemental agreement, 6/1/88; request for arbitration, 1987
- Pennsylvania Negotiation: 40 hours a week, Miscellaneous [folder 1 of 2], 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Letter from pres Jay Mazur re appointment of Sol Hoffman to chair Major Market Negotiations Task Force on 35 Hour Work Week, suggests there may be cases in which extending the week is acceptable with strict wage & employment guarantees, 12/17; memo to pres Mazur from Wilbur Daniels, 10/6, re attached draft of letter of agreement with Pennsylvania plants re 40 hr wk, lengthy analysis; Summary of wages and hours by plant (Andy, Downing, Glen Lion, Pittston, Ricky, Throop, Kingston), 1/1/84-12/31/86; estimated savings by various cost-cutting measures (eliminate three holidays, reconstruct rate structures, flexible 40 hr week, etc); revised volume differential, 3/4/86; draft agreements; employee records
- Pennsylvania Negotiation: 40 hours a week, Miscellaneous [folder 2 of 2], 1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Pennsylvania Negotiation: 40 hours a week, Minutes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Handwritten minutes of meetings 8/24, 8/27, 9/2, 10/5; typed transcripts: 8/6, cutting piece rates, increase to 40 hr work week; 8/3 major reduction in Wilkes-Barre, PA, cutting facility with layoffs of 50-70 long-term employees; 6/11, growth of imports; 4/9, Glen Lion plant doing poorly, propose to send more work if workers agree to 5% reduction in piece rate; Leslie Fay workers sometimes take pay increases in form of reduced output; import caps; guaranteed employment levels; wage guarantees 3/13, company needs to cut costs 30% to remain competitive w/imports: increase to 40 hrs., forgo scheduled 5% wage increase 3/4 proposed unilateral reduction in wages, increase in hours, no guarantees of employment; 2/19, longer hours at reduced piece rate, reducing employer contributions to health & welfare fund; imports; 2/11, competition w/ imports, esp from S. Korea, need 30% reduction in costs to remain competitive; union: if Leslie Fay gets 40 hr week, whole industry will want it
- Personal Sportswear: Morrow, GA, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Correspondence re use of non-union plant, Jorca (Hialeah, FL), 1986; drafts (some heavily hand annotated) and final signed supplemental agreement with side letters re shift differential, payment for time off for injury on the job, 6/1/85-5/31/88 and 6/1/88-5/31/91
- Sassco, Leslie Fay: Secaucus, NJ, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Arbitration decisions and opinions re suspension and discharges, unsigned master agreement governing employer payment of vacation pay directly to employees, 1987 & 88, letter of agreement re shutdown of Secaucus facility, severance pay, 1990; drafts and signed final copy of supplemental agreement, 6/1/88, with cover letters; 1985 agreement
- Spitalnick: Leslie Fay, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Correspondence re acquisition of Spitalnick by Leslie Fay, coverage by a different union agreement (copy of agreement included); correspondence re possible plant closing
- Stephanie Fashions: Roanoke, Alabama, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Drafts of supplemental agreements with correspondence
- Maidenform, Incorporated, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Letter to ILG pres. Jay Mazur from Maidenform VP re changes in the brassiere industry, competition with imports, need to cut costs, close Perth Amboy, NJ, plant, 1988; letter from Maidenform VP re need to use non-union contractors for panty production, 1988; master agreement, 1987; highlights of ILG/Maidenform relationship covering 1978-88; list of number of employees by seniority at Perth Amboy and Huntington, WV, plants; memo re closing of facility in Edison, NJ, 1987; handwritten notes, 1988
- Mode O'Day: Agreements, ILGWU, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  ILG agreement with Mode O'Day Division, Gamble-Skogmo, Inc., July 1, 1983; supplements covering Burbank, California; San Bernardino, California, and Salt Lake City, Utah; Hastings, Nebraska
- Mode O'Day: Agreements, ILGWU Drafts, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Drafts of agreements in Box 4 Folder 2.
- Mode O'Day: Agreements, Company Exhibits, 1968-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)